<cms path="/community" serve="true" type="html" locale="en_US" host="liftweb.net">
  <tag name="name" value="community"/>
  <tag name="menu" value="Community"/>
  <tag name="order" value="5"/>
  <content>
    <lift:surround with="default" at="content">
      <head>
	<title>Lift :: Community</title>
      </head>
      
   <div class="row-fluid">
      <div class="span12">

        <div class="row-fluid">
          <div class="span8">         
     <!--  <div id="left"> --> 
	<h1>The Lift Community</h1>
	<p>
	  The Lift community strives to be a warm and welcoming place to newbies and seasoned users alike.
	  If you've got a question, the community will try to provide a substantive answer (not RTFM.)
	</p>

	<p>
	  The <a href="http://groups.google.com/group/liftweb">Lift mailing list</a> is the official support channel for Lift.
	  The IRC channel is a popular, but unofficial, support channel for Lift.
	</p>
	
	<p>
	  The following are not ways to get support for Lift:
	  <ul>
	    <li>Personal email to one of the committers (unless you have a relationship with that committer)</li>
	    <li>Personal IM with the committers (unless you know them very well)</li>
	    <li>Twitter... the Lift committers don't monitor Twitter for Lift support requests</li>
	    <li>GitHub... don't use GitHub messages.  
	      None of the Lift committer will pull from your repository.  
	      The Lift IP is clean which means that unless you are a committer and you have written the code yourself, 
	      it doesn't get into Lift.  This allows businesses to use Lift knowing what the provenance of the code is.
	    </li>
	  </ul>
	</p>

	<p>
	  Please be polite on the Lift mailing list.  Please say "please" and "thank you."
	  The community tries to be timely with answers, but very often a question may not get an
	  answer for a few days.  Being a squeaky wheel about getting an answer will not make it
	  happen any faster.  There are people on the Lift list who are consultants.  If you need
	  support in a timely manner and are willing to pay, please make that offer.
	</p>

	<p>
	  Disagreements... there are plenty of ways to approach technical issues.  Lift was built from user 
	  feedback and we try to foster a community in which feedback is encouraged.  But this
	  implies certain ground rules:
	  <ul>
	    <li>You can disagree with a person's opinion, but please continue to respect the person</li>
	    <li>Using words like "nightmare", "sucks", and other similar words will not help your cause.
	    Please spend time working on the positives of your position rather than focusing on the
	    negatives of other peoples' positions.</li>
	    <li>You may have to agree to disagree</li>
	  </ul>
	</p>

	<p>
	  New member of the group are moderated (this radically reduces spam).  You may have to wait
	  2 to 24 hours for a post to be moderated.  Please do not repost the same question if you don't
	  see it show up immediately.
	</p>
	
	<p>
	  Lift is an open source project done entirely by volunteers.  The Lift documentation is not professional.
	  If you would like improvements to the documentation, please write wiki articles.  Posting complaints
	  about the documentation on the mailing list does not help it appear faster.  Posting questions
	  and summarizing the answer into a wiki post on the other hand will earn you faster and more detailed
	  answers in the future.
	</p>

	<p>
	  Please also read <a href="http://lift.la/the-loyal-opposition">The Loyal Opposition</a>.
	  Before opening a ticket, please discuss it on the Lift Google Group.  For more information,
	  <a href="https://www.assembla.com/wiki/show/liftweb/Creating_tickets">Creating Tickets</a>
	  outlines the rules for opening tickets.  We have this policy to keep Lift-related discussions
	  in the open and available to every community member.
	</p>
      <!--  </div> --><!-- left -->
          </div>      
	        <div class="span4">  
	          <lift:embed what="col2"/> 
            </div>
        </div>    
 
      </div>
    </div> 
    </lift:surround>
  </content>
</cms>
