<cms path="/team" serve="true" type="html" locale="en_US" host="liftweb.net">
	<tag name="name" value="team" />
	<tag name="menu" value=" Team" />
	<tag name="menu-icon" value="icon-user icon-white" />
	<tag name="menu-divider" value="vdivider" />
	<tag name="order" value="7" />
	<content>
		<lift:surround with="default" at="content">
			<head>
				<title>Lift :: Team</title>
			</head>

			<div class="row-fluid">
				<div class="span12">

					<div class="row-fluid">
						<div class="span9">
                            <div class="page-header">
                            <h1 id="current-team">CURRENT TEAM</h1>
                            </div>
							<div class="alert alert-info">An awful lot of time and effort has gone into
								making lift the great
								bit of software it is today - so, to honor this effort, we felt it
								only
								right to honor those who have generously donated time to the project.
							</div>
							<hr />
							
							
							<div>
								<h3>David
									Pollak &ndash;
									Founder
								</h3>
								<p>David Pollak has been writing commercial software since 1977.
									He wrote the
									first real-time spreadsheet and the worlds highest performance
									spreadsheet
									engine. Since 1996, David has been using and devising web development
									tools. As CTO
									of CMP Media, David oversaw the first large-scale deployment of
									WebLogic.
									David was CTO and VPE at Cenzic, a web application security company.
									David
									has also developed numerous commercial projects in Ruby on Rails.
									In 2007, David founded the Lift Framework open source project.
								</p>
							</div>

							<div>
								<h3>Tyler Weir</h3>
								<p>Currently a co-founder of Roboboogie Studios. In my former
									jobs I
									worked on compilers, desktop business apps and web applications.
									Along with Derek and Marius, I'm a co-author of the upcoming
									Lift
									book.
								</p>
							</div>
							<div>
								<h3>Derek Chen-Becker</h3>
								<p>A senior network engineer for a large company. I've been
									doing software
									development for over 14 years, with 12 years of Java experience. I started
									working with Scala 2 years ago and I've been working heavily
									with Lift since
									version 0.2 came out.
								</p>
							</div>

							<div>
								<h3>Indrajit Raychaudhuri</h3>
								<p>Indrajit manages Lift's builds and build environment
									including some serious mastery of both Maven and SBT.
								</p>
							</div>

							<div>
								<h3>Vassil Dichev</h3>
								<p>Vassil is a Lift user in the ESME project and
									contributes to Lift's TestKit.
								</p>
							</div>

							<div>
								<h3>Mads Hartmann Jensen</h3>
								<p>Mads is a energetic young developer from Copenhagen, Denmark.
									He's been a Lift committer since January 2010 and has been
									working on different parts of Lift. As part of his Google
									Summer of Code project in 2010 he created Lifty to make Lift
									developers more productive . When he's not caught up in various
									open source projects he's getting his bachelor in software
									development at the IT University of Copenhagen.</p>
							</div>

							<div>
								<h3>Jeppe Nejsum Madsen</h3>
								<p>Co-founder and CTO of FleetZone, a company that builds a SaaS
									platform for fleet management (based on Lift of course!).</p>
							</div>

							<div>
								<h3>Andreas Joseph Krogh</h3>
								<p>No description available.</p>
							</div>

							<div>
								<h3>Torsten Uhlmann</h3>
								<p>No description available.</p>
							</div>

							<div>
								<h3>Dave Whittaker</h3>
								<p>Dave maintains Lift's Squeryl-Record code.</p>
							</div>

							<div>
								<h3>Ján Raška</h3>
								<p>Ján contributes to Lift's Squeryl-Record code.</p>
							</div>

							<div>
								<h3>Franz Bettag</h3>
								<p>Black Belt DevOp, CEO and Developer located in Nuremberg,
									Germany. Franz has written some excellent examples for Lift and
									gave an awesome presentation about Lift and Akka at the Scala
									Lift Off London 2011. He's been active in the Community for
									quite some time and became Lift committer in January 2012.</p>
							</div>

							<div>
								<h3>Diego Medina</h3>
								<p>Diego is a super helpful, super excellent, super nice, and
									super skilled member of the Lift community. He's been active in
									the Community for quite some time and became Lift committer in
									Mars 2012.</p>
							</div>

							<div>
								<h3>Peter Petersson</h3>
								<p>Peter is a system developer at Avalon Innovation. He is a senior 
								Java developer that has found his way to Scala and Lift. He's been 
								active in the Community for some time and became Lift committer in 
								May 2012.</p>
							</div>
							<hr />
							<h1 id="alumni-team">ALUMNI TEAM</h1>

							<p>As Lift has grown, the team has expanded and contracted over
								time. However, the work done by
								team members that are not currently active also deserves credit, so
								they are listed
								here as Alumni members.
							</p>

							<div>
								<h3>Timothy Perrett</h3>
								<p>Technical Architect / Geek / Open source junkie - specializes
									in
									systems integration for manufacturing and workflow systems. Has been
									working
									with Scala since the end of 07' and before that was working with
									Java, Ruby
									and Objective-C extensively for a number of years. Also a
									repentant Rails convert.
									Whilst not working on Lift I work for an Israeli startup designing
									systems
									for techno-marketing and on-demand publishing.
								</p>
							</div>

							<div>
								<h3>Marius Danciu</h3>
								<p>Marius has been a committer for more than an year now
									contributing with design and development
									of new features as well as fixing defects. I discovered Scala
									about 2-3 years ago
									and coming from Java world it's needless to say how much that
									impressed me.
									For the past 6 years I've been architecting,designing and
									developing server
									side Java applications orbiting around synchronization technologies
									such as
									SyncML. Before that I've been doing C/C++ programming.
								</p>
							</div>

							<div>
								<h3>Jonathan Hoffman</h3>
								<p>Jon crontributed Lift's image management library
									and puts Lift to the test every day.
								</p>
							</div>

							<div>
								<h3>Debby Meredith</h3>
								<p>I'm a currently an engineering management consultant and a
									venture partner at JAFCO
									Ventures. I work hands-on with company founders, helping to assemble
									world class teams,
									architect software products and roadmaps, and establish operational
									processes to
									build success from the beginning. Previously, I was a venture
									partner at Mohr Davidow
									Ventures, VP Eng at Netscape, VP Eng at Collabra Software, VP Eng at
									Slate Software,
									and had key technical positions at Metaphor Computer Systems,
									Logitech, and Bell Laboratories.
								</p>
							</div>
							<div>
								<h3>Heiko Seeberger</h3>
								<p>
									Heiko Seeberger is an OSGi expert and Scala enthusiast. He is
									managing director of WeigleWilczek, a German consulting company
									specializing in Scala and other cool technologies. Heiko is
									also an active open source committer, e.g. to Lift, Akka and
									ScalaModules.
								</p>
							</div>
							<div>
								<h3>Jonas Bonér</h3>
								<p>Jonas Bonér is a programmer, mentor, speaker and author who
									spends
									most of his time consulting, hacking Scala as well as lecturing and
									speaking at developer conferences world-wide. He has worked at
									Terracotta, the JRockit JVM at BEA and is an active contributor
									to the
									Open Source community; most notably created the AspectWerkz
									Aspect-Oriented Programming (AOP) framework, committer to the
									Terracotta JVM clustering technology and been part of the
									Eclipse
									AspectJ team. He is a passionate Scala and FP enthusiast and a
									programming languages geek in general.
								</p>
							</div>

							<div>
								<h3>Jorge Ortiz</h3>
								<p>Jorge Ortiz has programmed in C/C++, Java, Ruby, and Python
									before settling on Scala as his language of choice. He
									presented Scala and Lift at JavaOne 2008's ScriptBowl. He has
									taught a class on Scala at Stanford University and one on Lift
									with David Pollak.</p>
							</div>
							<div>
								<h3>Eric Torreborre</h3>
								<p>
									Eric runs the
									<a href="http://code.google.com/p/specs/">Specs</a>
									project
									and contributes to Lift's test suite and testing methodology.
								</p>
							</div>

							<div>
								<h3>Ross Mellgren</h3>
								<p>Ross writes and maintains much of Lift's Record NoSQL code.
								</p>
							</div>

							<div>
								<h3>Harry Heymann</h3>
								<p>Harry contributed Lift's OAuth module and writes a
									lot of code that makes hard-core real-world use of Lift.
								</p>
							</div>



							<div>
								<h3>David Bernard</h3>
								<p>No description available.</p>
							</div>
							<div>
								<h3>Kris Nuttycombe</h3>
								<p>No description available.</p>
							</div>


							<div>
								<h3>Steve Jenson</h3>
								<p>Steve added the XMPP and AMQP components of Lift. He
									currently
									lives in San Francisco with his wife and cats and works at Twitter,
									Inc.
								</p>
							</div>
							<div>
								<h3>Daniel Green</h3>
								<p>Daniel Green is a FLOSS advocate and musician from the Boston
									area.</p>
							</div>

							<div>
								<h3>Alex Boisvert</h3>
								<p>No description available..</p>
							</div>
							<div>
								<h3>Alex Payne</h3>
								<p>No description available..</p>
							</div>
							<div>
								<h3>Burak Emir</h3>
								<p>No description available..</p>
							</div>
							<div>
								<h3>Carsten</h3>
								<p>No description available..</p>
							</div>
							<div>
								<h3>Philipp Schmidt</h3>
								<p>No description available..</p>
							</div>
							<div>
								<h3>Maciek Starzyk</h3>
								<p>No description available..</p>
							</div>
							<div>
								<h3>Julien Wetterwald</h3>
								<p>No description available..</p>
							</div>
							<div>
								<h3>Stepan Koltsov</h3>
								<p>No description available..</p>
							</div>

							<div>
								<h3>Viktor Klang</h3>
								<p>A Senior Systems Analyst / Architect / Project Manager /
									Developer / whatnot at a large company. I've been doing
									enterprise-level software development the past 7 years, I've
									gone through quite a few programming languages but for the past
									9 years it's been Java, and the past 2 years I've been into
									Scala adventures.
								</p>
							</div>

							<div>
								<h3>Chris Wilkes</h3>
								<p>No description available..</p>
							</div>
							<div>
								<h3>Al Thompson</h3>
								<p>No description available..</p>
							</div>
							<div>
								<h3>Francois Bertrand</h3>
								<p>No description available..</p>
							</div>

						</div>
						<div id="col2" class="span3">
							<lift:embed what="col2" />
						</div>
					</div>

				</div>
			</div>
		</lift:surround>
	</content>
</cms>
