<cms path="/10_release" serve="true" type="html" locale="en_US" 
     host="liftweb.net" valid_from="2009/02/26">
  <tag name="sub" value="happening">
    Lift 1.0 Released!
  </tag>
  <tag name="desc">
    2009/02/26 - After months of development, we're proud to announce the release of Lift 1.0
  </tag>
  <content>
    <lift:surround with="default" at="content" >
      <head>
	<title>Lift :: 1.0 Release</title>
      </head>
      
    <div class="row-fluid">
      <div class="span12">

        <div class="row-fluid">
          <div class="span9">  
            
	<p>
	  <b>Hey
	    Web Developer – Need a Lift
	    (1.0)? </b>
	</p>
	<p >
	  <br />
	</p>
	<p align="center">
	  <i>Promising
	    New Web Framework Now
	    Available for Download; Developers Applaud Framework’s ‘Conciseness
	    of Ruby with the Compile Times Performance of Java’</i></p>
	<p>
	  <br />
	</p>
	<p>
	  <b>San
	    Francisco–
	    February 26, 2009 –</b>
	  On the eve of the <u><a href="http://liftweb.net/"></a></u>
	  Project’s second anniversary, the creators and early adopters of
	  the Scala-based open source web framework toasted beers and heavily
	  caffeinated beverages across the globe as they made version 1.0
	  available for download (web link here)at http://liftweb.net.</p>
	<p >
	  <br />
	</p>
	<p >
	  “Each
	  new major era of software development began with a problem that
	  traditional languages and design patterns could not solve,” said
	  David Pollak, creator of Lift.  “If the current technical
	  challenges of Facebook, Twitter and massive multi-player online games
	  are harbingers, it’s pretty clear that it’s time again for a new
	  programming language and a new development framework to foster
	  efficient delivery of a whole new generation of applications and web
	  services.  Today, we’re here to say that Scala and Lift are the new
	  guard, built specifically for the future challenges of web
	  development.”</p>
	<p>
	  <br />
	</p>
	<p>
	  While
	  Lift has
	  been too nascent for the mainstream thus far, it has quietly become
	  indispensable for the developers of the next generation of consumer
	  web and enterprise development projects that involve highly
	  interactive web sites.  To date, more than a dozen developers are
	  working on the open-source project across Asia, Europe and the United
	  States and there are approximately 20 applications of Lift in
	  commercial production including <u><a CLASS="western" href="http://buyafeature.com/">Buy
	      a Feature</a></u>
	  (http://buyafeature.com).</p>
	<p>
	  <br />
	</p>
	<p>
	  “Lift's
	  excellent 'Comet –made- easy' philosophy made it an absolute
	  no-brainer as the choice of framework for the Apache ESME project,”
	  said Darren Hauge, SAP Mentor and ESME Team Lead.  “Additionally,
	  the fact that Lift-based applications run unchanged on the SAP's
	  NetWeaver CE Java application server makes an intriguing approach for
	  enterprise applications in the SAP world.”</p>
	<p>
	  <br />
	</p>
	<p >
	  Mr.
	  Hauge, as well as many
	  other developers, have
	  realized the following benefits:</p>
	<p>
	  <br />
	</p>
	<ul>
	  <li><p>
	      Lift
	      is a
	      faster way to build multi-person, highly interactive web sites,
	      fully deployable on J2EE stack</p>
	  </li>

	  <li>
	    <p>
	      Superior
	      development and runtime performance
	      and scalability 
	    </p>
	  </li>
	  
	  <li><p>
	      Lift
	      applications
	      are more secure than those built with other popular frameworks
	    </p>
	  </li>

	  <li>
	    <p>
	      Lift
	      works
	      with existing Java libraries and tools
	    </p>
	  </li>

	  <li>
	    <p>
	      Real
	      time multiperson interactive web sites run better on Lift than
	      anything else
	    </p>
	  </li>
	
	  <li>
	    <p>
	      Scala
	      (ruby+Java greatness in one),
	      plus smart folks in the open source project
	    </p>
	  </li>
	
	  <li>
	    <p>
	      Crazy
	      J2EE-class
	      scalability, don't without having to give up runtime for
	      development performance
	    </p>
	  </li>
	</ul>
	
	<p>
	  Developers
	  can prototype
	  applicationss in a matter of days in a small community (much like
	  Rails)
	</p>
	
	<p>
	  <br />
	</p>
	
	<p>“The
	  interest and excitement about Scala continues to grow. &nbsp;It’s
	  great to see Lift reaching the 1.0 milestone as this is a proof point
	  for the maturity of Scala as a software platform,” said Martin
	  Odersky, ACM Fellow, and father of Scala.</p>
	<p><br /><br />
	</p>
     
          </div>      
	        <div class="span3">  
	          <lift:embed what="col2"/> 
            </div>
        </div>     
        </div>  
      </div>  
    </lift:surround>
  </content>
</cms>
