<cms path="/20_ga" serve="true" type="html" locale="en_US" 
     valid_from="2010/06/30" host="liftweb.net">
<tag name="sub" value="happening">
  <b>Lift 2.0</b> Ships!
</tag>
<tag name="desc">
  2010/06/30 The Lift team is proud to announce version 2.0 of the Lift Web
  Framework
</tag>
<content>
  <lift:surround with="default" at="content" >
    <head>
      <title>Lift Web Framework :: 2.0 GA</title>
    </head>

    
    <div id="left">
      <div>
	    <h1>Announcing Lift 2.0</h1>
	    <p>June 30th, 2010<br />
	    </p>
	    <p>The <a href="http://liftweb.net">Lift</a> team and the <a href="http://groups.google.com/group/liftweb">Lift community</a> are proud to announce the availability of <a href="http://liftweb.net/download.html">Lift 2.0</a><br />
	    </p>
	    
	    <p>
	      <blockquote>"Lift is the kind of web framework that enables you as a developer to
		concentrate on the big picture. Strong, expressive typing and
		higher-level features like the built-in Comet support allow you to
		focus on innovating instead of the plumbing. Building a rich, real-time
		web application like Novell Pulse requires a framework with the power
		of Lift under the covers."
	      </blockquote>
	      <span style="margin-left: 80px">- David LaPalomento, Developer, Novell</span>
	    </p>

	    <p>
	      <blockquote>
		"Foursquare switched over to Scala &amp; Lift last September and
		we've been thrilled with the results.  The ease of developing complex
		interactive ajax web pages enabled a very rapid port from our previous
		platform.  In addition, the support we've gotten from David Pollak and
		the rest of the Lift team has been invaluable. It's clear they are
		very committed to making sure that production Lift deployments get all
		the attention they need to succeed."
	      </blockquote>
	      <span style="margin-left: 80px">- @harryh, Foursquare Engineering Tech Lead</span>
	    </p>
	    
	    <p>Lift is an elegant, expressive web framework that allows any size
	      team build and maintain secure, highly interactive, scalable web
	      applicationsquickly and efficiently.&nbsp; Lift is built on the  <a href="http://scala-lang.org">Scala</a> and compiles
	      to JVM byte-code.&nbsp; Lift applications deploy as WAR files on
	      popular application servers and web cotainers including Jetty,
	      Glassfish and Tomcat.&nbsp; Lift applications can be monitored and
	      managed with the same proven infrastructure used to manage and monitor
	      any Java web application.&nbsp; Lift is open source licensed under an Apache 2.0 license.<br />
	    </p>
	    <h2>Lift features include:<br />
	    </h2>
	    <ul>
	      <li>Community... the Lift community is 2,000 members strong, super-active and always there to help with questions</li>
	      <li>Best Comet (server-push) support that allows the creation of dynamic application such as <a href="http://www.novell.com/products/pulse/">Novell Pulse</a></li>
	      <li>Super simple Ajax for creating highly interactive web applications without worrying about HTTP plumbing<br />
	      </li>
	      <li>Secure by default... Lift apps are resistant to the OWASP top 10 vulnerabilities including XSS, XSRF, and parameter tampering<br />
	      </li>
	      <li>Concise and Maintainable... Lift apps typically contain fewer
		lines of code than corresponding Rails apps, yet are type safe so that
		many errors are flagged by the compiler<br />
	      </li>
	      <li>Scalable... Lift apps scale to millions of users across many servers, yet are highly efficient for single-box implementations</li>
	      <li>Compatible... Lift apps can take advantage of any Java library as well as the growing collection of Scala libraries<br />
	      </li>
	    </ul>
	    <h2>Lift 2.0's new features include:</h2>
	    <ul>
	      <li>NoSQL support including built-in support for MongoDB and CouchDB</li>
	      <li>High performance JSON support including an elegant JSON DSL and bidirectional JSON &lt;-&gt; Class conversion</li>
	      <li>Powerful, concise REST support<br />
	      </li>
	      <li>Support for enterprise infrastructure including JTA and LDAP</li>
	      <li>Declarative systems for single <a href="https://liftweb.assembla.com/wiki/show/liftweb/Lift%27s_Screen">Screen</a> input and validation as well as multiple screen Wizards</li>
	      <li>Radically
		improved development experience including much better error messages
		and support for dynamically changing system configuration</li>
	      <li>Support for running Lift apps outside of a J/EE Servlet containers</li>
	      <li>Improved Comet support including modern browser detection and better connection starvation detection</li>
	      <li>Improved support for testing including super-concise dependency injection and run-mode detection</li>
	      <li>Support for <a href="http://code.google.com/p/simple-build-tool/">Simple Build Tool</a></li>
	      <li>Performance improvements</li>
	    </ul>
	    <h2>Lift-powered sites include:</h2>
	    <ul>
	      <li><a href="http://foursquare.com">Foursquare</a> -- the multi-million
		user location based service that will soon surpass 1M+ checkins a day
		on their Lift-powered system
	      </li>
	      <li><a href="http://www.novell.com/products/pulse/">Novell</a> <a href="http://www.vimeo.com/7443817">Pulse</a> -- enterprise collaboration software platform based on Google Wave<br />
	      </li>
	      <li><a href="http://www.xmpie.com">Xerox/XMPie</a> -- the leading provider of software for cross-media, variable data one-to-one marketing<br />
	      </li>
	      <li><a href="http://snapsort.com/">Snapsort</a> -- Compare and decide on cameras</li>
	      <li><a href="http://nofouls.com/">No Fouls</a> -- Find pickup basketball games<br />
	      </li>
	    </ul>
	    Please join the Lift community and help use grow Lift.&nbsp; And a
	    super-big thanks to the 30+ Lift committers who have grown the Lift
	    community and code-base to what it is today... and what it will be in
	    the future!<br />
	    <br />
	    <br />
	    
      </div>
    </div><!--left-->
  </lift:surround>
</content>
</cms>
