<cms path="/25_m1" serve="true" type="html" locale="en_US" host="liftweb.net" valid_from="2012/09/09">
  <tag name="sub" value="happening">
    <b>Lift 2.5-M1</b> Ships!
  </tag>

  <tag name="desc">
    2012/10/12 The Lift team is proud to announce version 2.5-M1 of Lift.
  </tag>

  <content>
    <lift:surround with="default" at="content">
      <head>
        <title>Lift :: 2.5-M1</title>
      </head>
    <div class="row-fluid">
      <div class="span12">

        <div class="row-fluid">
          <div class="span9">  
            
        <div>
          <div class="page-header">
          <h1>Announcing Lift 2.5-M1</h1>
          </div>
          <em>September 12, 2012</em>

          <p>The Lift team proudly announces the <a href="/download">availability</a>
            of the Milestone 1 release of Lift version 2.5.
          </p>
          <p>Lift is a powerful, secure and most matured web framework available today. There are
            <a href="http://seventhings.liftweb.net/" target="_blank">Seven Things</a>
            that distinguish Lift from other web frameworks.
          </p>

          <p>Lift applications are:</p>
          <ul>
            <li>Secure -- Lift apps are resistant to common vulnerabilities including many of the OWASP Top 10</li>
            <li>Developer centric -- Lift apps are fast to build, concise and easy to maintain</li>
            <li>Scalable -- Lift apps are high performance and scale in the real world to handle insane traffic levels</li>
            <li>Interactive like a desktop app -- Lift's Comet support is unparalleled and Lift's ajax support is super-easy and very secure</li>
          </ul>

          <p>Read an <a href="/lift_overview">overview</a> of how Lift achieves these important goals.</p>

          <p>Lift open source software licensed under an Apache 2.0 license.</p>

          <p>Lift 2.5 includes the following new features and enhancements:</p>
          <ul>
            <li>Improved jsonCall methods. Based on the powerful lift-json library</li>
            <li>Upgraded Squeryl to version 0.9.5</li>
            <li>Unified resource lookup (i18n), giving you the option to override Lift's core messages</li>
            <li>Lots of improvements to the Comet support</li>
            <li>LiftScreen now supports very flexible CSS styling</li>
            <li>Lift now uses specs2</li>
            <li>The Lift modules were moved to a new <a href="https://github.com/organizations/liftmodules">repository</a> and organization, allowing external contributions</li>
            <li>Updated Lift <a href="https://github.com/lift/lift_25_sbt">templates</a></li>
          </ul>

          <p>A complete list of changes that made it into 2.5-M1 can be found at:</p>
          <ul>
            <li><a href="https://github.com/lift/framework/issues?milestone=20&amp;page=1&amp;state=closed">Tickets on github</a></li>
          </ul>

          <p>Please join the <a href="https://groups.google.com/group/liftweb" target="_blank">Lift Community</a>
            and enjoy building awesome apps with Lift.</p>

        </div>
          </div>      
	        <div class="span3">  
	          <lift:embed what="col2"/> 
            </div>
        </div>     
        </div>  
      </div> 
    </lift:surround>
  </content>
</cms>
