<cms path="/26_m3" serve="true" type="html" locale="en_US" host="liftweb.net" valid_from="2014/04/12">
  <tag name="sub" value="happening">
    <b>Lift 2.6 M3</b>
  </tag>

  <tag name="desc">
    2014/04/12 The Lift team is proud to announce Milestone 3 of Lift 2.6.
  </tag>

  <content>
    <lift:surround with="default" at="content">
      <head>
        <title>Lift :: 2.6 M3</title>
      </head>
    <div class="row-fluid">
      <div class="span12">

        <div class="row-fluid">
          <div class="span9">  
            
        <div>
          <div class="page-header">
          <h1>Announcing Lift 2.6 M3</h1>
          </div>
          <em>April 12, 2014</em>

          <p>The Lift team proudly announces the <a href="/download">availability</a>
            of Milestone 3 of Lift version 2.6.
          </p>
          <p>Lift is the most powerful, secure and mature web framework available today. There are
            Seven Things
            that distinguish Lift from other web frameworks.
          </p>

          <p>Lift applications are:</p>
          <ul>
            <li>Secure -- Lift apps are resistant to common vulnerabilities including many of the OWASP Top 10</li>
            <li>Developer centric -- Lift apps are fast to build, concise and easy to maintain</li>
            <li>Scalable -- Lift apps are high performance and scale in the real world to handle insane traffic levels</li>
            <li>Interactive like a desktop app -- Lift's Comet support is unparalleled and Lift's ajax support is super-easy and very secure</li>
            <li>Modular -- Lift apps can benefit from, easy to integrate, pre built modules</li>
            <li>Designer friendly -- Lift apps can be developed in a totally designer friendly way</li>
          </ul>
          <p>Read an <a href="/lift_overview">overview</a> of how Lift achieves these important goals.</p>
          <p>Lift open source software licensed under an Apache 2.0 license.</p>
          
          <!-- **** START OF CHANGES PASTED FROM GITHUB RELEASE NOTES *********************** -->

          <div class="markdown-body">

            <h3>Notable Changes</h3>

            <ul>
              <li><a href="https://github.com/lift/framework/pull/1523">Box.get is officially deprecated</a>. Previously, calling <code>.get</code> on a box would trigger an implicit conversion from Box =&gt; Option. As we move towards encouraging people even more to utilize flatMap, map, etc to open boxes and to specify exceptions when they can't (a la <code>openOrThowException</code>), we're officially deprecating the use of <code>.get</code> on a box, and you will start seeing warnings in your code if you do it as of this release. In Lift 3.0, the ability to call <code>.get</code> on a box will disappear.</li>
            </ul>
            
            <h3>New Features / Enhancements</h3>

            <ul>
              <li><a href="https://github.com/lift/framework/pull/1500">Case class decomposition performance improvements.</a> By doing some clever code <a href="https://github.com/chriswebster" class="user-mention">@chriswebster</a> was able to bring the complexity of case class decomposition down to O(n).</li>
              <li><a href="https://github.com/lift/framework/pull/1517">Memoization to prevent additional reflection during decomposition</a>, also thanks to <a href="https://github.com/chriswebster" class="user-mention">@chriswebster</a>.</li>
              <li><a href="https://github.com/lift/framework/pull/1506">Implementation of LiftRules.funcNameGenerator.</a> You can now use your own logic for generating Func names. Thanks <a href="https://github.com/japgolly" class="user-mention">@japgolly</a></li>
              <li><a href="https://github.com/lift/framework/pull/1509">The Framework should be capable of compiling in Scala 2.10.1+ now</a> thanks to <a href="https://github.com/pbrant" class="user-mention">@pbrant</a>.</li>
              <li><a href="https://github.com/lift/framework/pull/1519">Some variable name cleanup in lift-json.</a></li>
              <li><a href="https://github.com/lift/framework/pull/1525">Implementation of toSingleBox</a> that converts a List[Box[T]] =&gt; Box[List[T]].</li>
            </ul>

            <h3>Bugfixes</h3>

            <ul>
              <li><a href="https://github.com/lift/framework/pull/1503">IE 11 detection is working.</a> IE changed their typical user agent signature in IE 11. The detection code has been updated to account for this change.</li>
              <li><a href="https://github.com/lift/framework/pull/1516">MockHttpServletRequest correctly handles empty parameters</a> thanks to contributions by <a href="https://github.com/dmclean62" class="user-mention">@dmclean62</a>.</li>
              <li><a href="https://github.com/lift/framework/pull/1521">Unexpected warnings related to page/instance resource IDs should no longer appear</a>, a hat tip to <a href="https://github.com/Shadowfiend" class="user-mention">@Shadowfiend</a> for that one.</li>
              <li><a href="https://github.com/lift/framework/pull/1526">Fixes for an issue where bad database connections wouldn't be released correctly</a>. Thanks to <a href="https://github.com/rofreytag" class="user-mention">@rofreytag</a> for this.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>




          <!-- **** END ********************************************************************* -->


          <p>Please join the <a href="https://groups.google.com/group/liftweb" target="_blank">Lift Community</a>
            and enjoy building awesome apps with Lift.</p>

        </div>
          </div>      
	        <div class="span3">  
	          <lift:embed what="col2"/> 
            </div>
        </div>     
        </div>  
      </div> 
    </lift:surround>
  </content>
</cms>
