<cms path="/30_rc1" serve="true" type="html" locale="en_US" host="liftweb.net" valid_from="2016/03/19">
  <tag name="sub" value="happening">
    <b>Lift 3.0-RC1</b>
  </tag>

  <tag name="desc">
    2016/03/19 The Lift team is proud to announce Release Candidate 1 of Lift 3.0.
  </tag>

  <content>
    <lift:surround with="default" at="content">
      <head>
        <title>Lift :: 3.0-RC1</title>
      </head>
    <div class="row-fluid">
      <div class="span12">

        <div class="row-fluid">
          <div class="span9">

        <div>
          <div class="page-header">
          <h1>Announcing Lift 3.0-RC1</h1>
          </div>
          <em>March 19, 2016</em>

          <p>The Lift team proudly announces the <a href="/download">availability</a>
            of Release Candidate 1 of Lift version 3.0.
          </p>
          <p>Lift is the most powerful, secure and mature web framework available today. There are
            <a href="http://seventhings.liftweb.net/" target="_blank">Seven Things</a>
            that distinguish Lift from other web frameworks.
          </p>

          <p>Lift applications are:</p>
          <ul>
            <li>Secure -- Lift apps are resistant to common vulnerabilities including many of the OWASP Top 10</li>
            <li>Developer centric -- Lift apps are fast to build, concise and easy to maintain</li>
            <li>Scalable -- Lift apps are high performance and scale in the real world to handle insane traffic levels</li>
            <li>Interactive like a desktop app -- Lift's Comet support is unparalleled and Lift's ajax support is super-easy and very secure</li>
            <li>Modular -- Lift apps can benefit from, easy to integrate, pre built modules</li>
            <li>Designer friendly -- Lift apps can be developed in a totally designer friendly way</li>
          </ul>
          <p>Read an <a href="/lift_overview">overview</a> of how Lift achieves these important goals.</p>
          <p>Lift open source software licensed under an Apache 2.0 license.</p>

          <!-- **** START OF CHANGES PASTED FROM GITHUB RELEASE NOTES *********************** -->

          <div class="markdown-body">

            <h3>Breaking Changes</h3>

            <ul>
              <li>
                <a class="issue-link" href="https://github.com/lift/framework/pull/1766">(#1766)</a> lift-json's <code>\\</code> used to return a JValue.
              In cases where it matched a single field directly, it would return the field's value rather than a consistent container type.
              Matching multiple fields would return a JObject with the matched fields in it.
              Now, <code>\\</code> always returns a **JObject** with the matching fields in it, even if there is only one such field.
              This may require adapting certain uses of <code>\\</code>, especially in for comprehensions.
              Code like <code>for (JString(name) <- object \\ "name")</code> will have to be changed to something more like
               <code>for (JField(_, JString(name)) <- object \\ "name")</code> to work correctly.
               Thanks to <a href="https://github.com/eallik">@eallik</a> for reporting!
             </li>
             <li>
               <a class="issue-link" href="https://github.com/lift/framework/pull/1773">(#1773)</a>,
               <a class="issue-link" href="https://github.com/lift/framework/pull/1779">(#1779)</a> Lift was depending on
               outdated versions of many libraries.
               We've bumped those dependencies, so we now depend on **specs2 3.7** and **Java Servlet 3.1**.
               All other version bumps were non-major, including **lift-json-scalaz** now depending on **Scalaz 7.2**.
               See the dependency file's diff for the full breakdown of dependency updates.
             </li>
            </ul>
            <h3>Improvements</h3>
            <ul>
              <li>
                <a class="issue-link" href="https://github.com/lift/framework/pull/1772">(#1772)</a>
                 When JsCmds including Noop were combined with <code>&</code>, you would get a lot of empty lines,
                 since each Noop would emit some empty lines in those cases.
                 Now, we ignore Noop when combining <code>JsCmds</code>, which should lead to reduced noise in serialized JS output.
                 The most immediate impact is that page-specific JavaScript will be much more compact than it was before.
                Fixes
              </li>
              <li>
                <a class="issue-link" href="https://github.com/lift/framework/pull/1779">(#1779)</a> <code>Props.whereToLook</code> works
                correctly again. In **3.0-M8**, we expanded the abilities of <code>Props</code> to read from arbitrary sources.
                Unfortunately, in the process, we broke the <code>whereToLook</code> setting that allowed you to adjust the search paths
                for <code>Props</code> to look for named property files. This has been fixed in **RC1**.
                Thanks to <a href="https://github.com/serioga">@serioga</a> for reporting!
              </li>
              <li>
                <a class="issue-link" href="https://github.com/lift/framework/pull/1769">(#1769)</a> Lift's JavaScript settings customization
                was set up such that you couldn't override things provided by **Lift's liftVanilla** or **liftJQuery** objects.
                This is now fixed, so custom JavaScript settings can build on and override those base functions.
                Thanks to <a href="https://github.com/joescii">@joescii</a> for reporting… And fixing! ;)
              </li>
            </ul>
          </div>

          <!-- **** END ********************************************************************* -->


          <p>Please join the <a href="https://groups.google.com/group/liftweb" target="_blank">Lift Community</a>
            and enjoy building awesome apps with Lift.</p>

        </div>
          </div>
	        <div class="span3">
	          <lift:embed what="col2"/>
            </div>
        </div>
        </div>
      </div>
    </lift:surround>
  </content>
</cms>
