<cms path="/310-rc1" serve="true" type="html" locale="en_US" host="liftweb.net" valid_from="2017/06/18">
  <tag name="sub" value="happening">
    <b>Lift 3.1.0-RC1</b>
  </tag>
  <tag name="desc">
    2017/06/18 The Lift team is proud to announce the release of Lift 3.1.0-RC1.
  </tag>
  <content>
    <lift:surround with="default" at="content">
      <head>
        <title>Lift :: 3.1.0-RC1</title>
      </head>
    <div class="row-fluid">
      <div class="span12">
        <div class="row-fluid">
          <div class="span9">
            <div>
              <div class="page-header">
                <h1>Announcing Lift 3.1.0-RC1</h1>
              </div>
              <em>June 18, 2017</em>

              <p>
                The Lift team proudly announces the <a href="/download">availability</a>
                of Lift version 3.1.0-RC1. This will become the final 3.1.0 build at the end of June
		unless we need to release additional RCs.
              </p>
              <p>
                Lift is the most powerful, secure and mature web framework available today. There are
                Seven Things
                that distinguish Lift from other web frameworks.
              </p>

              <p>Lift applications are:</p>
              <ul>
                <li>Secure -- Lift apps are resistant to common vulnerabilities including many of the OWASP Top 10</li>
                <li>Developer centric -- Lift apps are fast to build, concise and easy to maintain</li>
                <li>Scalable -- Lift apps are high performance and scale in the real world to handle insane traffic levels</li>
                <li>Interactive like a desktop app -- Lift's Comet support is unparalleled and Lift's ajax support is super-easy and very secure</li>
                <li>Modular -- Lift apps can benefit from, easy to integrate, pre built modules</li>
                <li>Designer friendly -- Lift apps can be developed in a totally designer friendly way</li>
              </ul>
              <p>Read an <a href="/lift_overview">overview</a> of how Lift achieves these important goals.</p>
              <p>Lift open source software licensed under an Apache 2.0 license.</p>

              <!-- **** START OF CHANGES PASTED FROM GITHUB RELEASE NOTES *********************** -->
              <!-- Look at 2.6_rc2 for a sample of how we do RC/M releases -->
              <!-- **** END ********************************************************************* -->
              <h3 id="msrc">Release Notes</h3>
              <p>Please see the summary of all the changes that made it into Lift 3.1.0-RC1 <a href="https://github.com/lift/framework/releases/tag/3.1.0-RC1-release">here</a></p>
              <p>Please join the <a href="https://groups.google.com/group/liftweb" target="_blank">Lift Community</a>
                and enjoy building awesome apps with Lift.</p>
            </div>
          </div>
	        <div class="span3">
	          <lift:embed what="col2"/>
          </div>
        </div>
        </div>
      </div>
    </lift:surround>
  </content>
</cms>
